Okay, we'll call for the
Council from Monday, March 18, 2024
Public in but on schedule personal passes. We have none. Three claims list
Much improved
All right,
five budget payment 24-11
Air portion,
Receipts and expending the jet fuel cells that are
A bud budget 2,6,031,
$366.
This is a good problem.
They have made more than they've budgeted in revenue,
But they've spent more than expenditure
And they let the budget is.
So we're just trying to bring everything back up.
So they can suffer.
They spent it, but we're making their budget balance.
Marc camer.
Aye.
Aye and then you'll contract a service bar on Shuacks administrator's hood.
Remove還是 que procedure, we are an electric vehicle.
They've talked about all our car contract documents in the possibility of it.
Unfortunately, all you're worthy is clearance for money for cars.
Let's establish costs on a potentially normal cost return of the car.
We can attach these products to your caviar, to our tenía potrzeby, to our job.
Hi.
7.
Purchase of a 2020-3-4 F-150 crew cab for the fire department, using all of the county fire cells,
tax funds.
Do you think you can get the new truck?
Yes.
The new crew.
The new truck.
So the county collects at 1-2 cents sales tax for fire departments to use.
They hold it and divide it.
I believe eight ways for each department in the county.
And we can use that for equipment, vehicles, training, general operating stuff.
So it's need your approval tonight to use part of what we have to purchase it.
2023, 4 F-150, it's $45,000, $210 in 20 cents.
And we've set that up on that three year lease through Welch State Bank.
And kind of the interesting part of this is that it's since the county collects the whole
so the funds will actually be owned by the county and shared by the county.
It's only for use in the mine of fire departments.
And that's all lit up.
It will be.
What color is it going to be?
Red.
Red flames on this side.
It's going to be cool.
Make a motion when I approve.
Second.
Eastern.
So four.
One.
Second.
Dot.
Hey.
Discussion on urban.
community forestry grant program that we bring forty-five in on here. It's through the
open Forestry Service in cooperation with the USDA Forestry Service. What it is, it's a
urban and community forestry cost shared grant. What they do is they're bringing the
resource. We're reinforcing these small communities putting trees back into these areas that may
not have the funds and the ability to do so. I'm applied for it and we're just looking for your
bit. Apply for is twenty-two thousand five hundred dollars. We're going to place these trees back
in the river report. Yeah, many trees are going to be. We're looking to place on this one
up to twenty-two. Terrific. Yeah, you know what kind we're looking to place a native
graphic of the college. All of the around fifty. There are native trees. They seem to thrive in
that area. I don't know if they'll bring it back in. You know all going to the river you park area. Yes,
both sides of the river are right now where as a Thursday of this week I have a company coming in
with phase one of this kind of project we already had going. It was sort of 550 trees in there
on the east side of that board. Well that's the hundred fifty part of the two fifty? No.
No. Told the river program. You know, probably we'd already had started. So you've got four hundred
trees but I don't know. It's all seven of that, yes, right? The bulk of these trees will probably go over
on the west side of the two fifty. It's a matter of grants. So this is probably five different
yards of wood. When do you find out? Kind of reading through the grant process here that they're looking
to move pretty quickly. It closes on the 29th of this month fully within. That's phenomenal. Good work.
I'm making motion. I'm sorry.
How big good storage from Linda?
Thank you.
Since, uh, especially if they got off the bat cutting them, that was now.
Yeah.
They didn't get on to us.
I got on to you.
It's definitely the agreement with best friend of the animal society, you may see.
Best friend of the animal society since 2020.
The group started in 2018.
It was kind of inspired by the Kirkpacker Foundation, not of Oklahoma City.
They got together in a meeting, and basically kind of talked about shelters in the area
and decided what can Oklahoma do because Oklahoma is so far behind animal welfare
standards that's compared to the rest of the nation.
So they created a initiative called Common Bonds, but a gentleman named Kelly Burley in the
director position of that.
He reached out to me in January of 2020, and by the need to a shelter meeting, it was just sheltered
from across the state.
We got together, roundtable discussion, I kind of like where it went, like getting together with
everybody and talking.
So I continued to do that through 2020, through even today, and as the years progressed, we kept
getting together and we kept having these meetings and talking.
I attended the shelter seminar, put on by the Oklahoma Animal Control Association, last
year in November, and that was actually led by Kelly Burley and Best Friend's Animal Society at
the time.
I brought in people from all over the nation to talk and educate us about where we were lacking
what we can do better in just general information.
It was a really cool seminar to attend.
It was two days seminar held in Moroble, and they kind of pulled me aside and talked
to me then of both any and common bonds have been in touch with me and have really liked the
direction that my Emma is going with their ordinances and their shelter practices.
So we got together and they told me that they may be combining, and common bonds may
be becoming embedded in Best Friend's, but it wasn't a done meal yet.
In January they reached out to me and told me that it was a done meal and they had decided
build a program and then tell me kind of what that program is. They kind of left me open-ended.
So you guys know best-ranking animals society is a non-profit organization based out of Utah.
They operate the nation's largest sanctuary for homeless animals. They provide low-cost Bay and newter options across the nation.
They have
several shelters themselves that they call life-saving centers. They're huge operations. One just opened in
Northwest Arkansas over the last year and they house about 2,500 animals there at any given time.
And then they also provide just general education services and literature to everybody that they can reach.
So when they finally reached out to me about the program that they put together, they broke Oklahoma up into
11 sections and we're looking for
district captains to run each section.
They offered me a
chance to become the district captain of Northeast Oklahoma for their group.
So the goal is to help strengthen the relationship with the shelters in Northeast Oklahoma.
And try to get some information about open doors that haven't been opened in Oklahoma.
The shelters in Oklahoma are pretty closed off.
Like I said, a lot of our
ordinances and state ordinances are far behind where they need to be.
So it's mainly to strengthen those relationships and talk and open those doors with other communities.
There's not a lot of information about what everybody in Oklahoma is doing as far as shelters.
There's not a lot of information on numbers
or, you know, a lot of cities aren't getting the credit they deserve for saving the animals they do.
And then at the same time we have some shelters that maybe almost completely kill shelters that we don't know about because people don't know how to get their information out there.
Or don't know how to ask for it.
So the goal of that group is to not only encourage people, it's not showing people, but to bring everybody together and see what other places are doing right where we can help.
And help move these animals and help get everybody to a.
Hopefully 90% library reached right across Oklahoma by the end of 2025.
I don't know if you guys keep up with any of that, but Utah actually just became the first no kill state.
So that's where this group's located out of.
They did it in Utah. They think we can do it here. This is the first state that they are implementing this type of program.
This is just a brief and outline of.
that they have a approximate time commitment,
they said, let's do a few about five hours a month,
to take depending on what we're doing
and how we're outwraging that month.
There's your nine sections.
I go out to one, and which it doesn't have an annual control
at the time.
There's a few that we're learning.
They're annual control departments.
I'm unfortunately shut down.
And then a few places that I found
that we didn't know even offered an annual control
until we started reaching out.
And then down to the Biscoggy area.
And it has started contacting these places
and kind of getting a feel for the communities
and what they need.
Obviously we're assessing needs.
While we're making those phone calls
or interacting in person, the goal is to help everybody
like said achieve that 90% library literature.
Or see what we need to do to close that gap.
And then encourage all these shelters
to report their shelter numbers,
and take out, take out things, come in, and how things lead.
So we know how to better assess
a whole home that's needs.
And where that legislation's needed
or where just general help is needed
for these small communities across Oklahoma.
And then any information that's fed to us verbally,
we are reporting that back to common bonds
and best friends via our Zoom calls or spreadsheets
that we put together with information as we collect it.
Part of this was we signed a memorandum of understanding
on February 28th, oh, and I signed it.
And as part of that, MOU, they granted our shelter,
a one-time grant, the amount of $6,500.
$5,000 of that is to be used within our own shelter
to help continue the life-saving that we are doing.
And then 1500 of it was to help offset
any expense and curd for a travel or anything like that.
If we want to host a meeting or whatever, it's called paper.
Catering, gas, to get to and formally decided to go in person.
I sent the W9, they're hoping to get our check test
within the next week.
I don't even know if that will be receiving that soon.
And then as of now, this is a one-time MOU
and it is effective through December 29th, 2024.
By next year, I'm sure if everything goes as planned,
they will renew those and we will go another year.
for you guys, do you guys have any questions on that?
I have a question. Back on your map, what was the significance of the color?
Various colors on there.
So the colors on here is each district.
Okay. So we have to just like our corner had like three different colors and I was just curious.
So this is the Tulsa area.
Okay.
So there's two district captains in Tulsa being a Various, so big and there's so many shelters.
Gotcha. Okay. I see the lines now.
Yep. And then Oklahoma City areas, another one.
And how to? And then there were some people along the I-40 corridor that had connections
of the shelters already. So we just stuffed them in their districts.
Thank you.
So you're very welcome.
I appreciate your dedication to this.
And I think it's important. I mean, I'm an animal lover myself.
And I see the things that we're doing in this.
It's positive.
Everywhere that I have talked to and have sent our ordinances.
I get asked for our ordinances all the time that you guys helped pass and you guys reviewed.
Everybody is blown away by own.
They really like what we're doing up here.
And we, I know that town is catching a lot of momentum, but our shelter has a lot of momentum.
And we're definitely on the right path on the right track.
We're setting standards for other communities in the States.
Hopefully we can keep doing this.
And then with this MOU and being part of this group,
hopefully we can continue to be at the forefront of all of those movements as we move forward.
The shelter's so full of all the time.
Yeah.
Yeah. We're full, full.
Oh, appreciate the work.
And your team put in.
Thank you very much.
The comment is basically, you continue to just be an exceptional leader.
You have shown that not only in our town, but now statewide.
This group clearly recognizes you in the transformational work you've been able to do with our ordinances with our community.
So I just hope you know how proud we are that we have you here in our town.
Making this transformation and putting again my am on the map.
For not only all the things we're doing and growing, but how we care for animals and that there's a better way to do government.
And so thank you for being so dedicated and doing such a wonderful job.
Thank you.
10.
How do the new businesses of Andy, which is risen?
Supposing this agenda.
11 staff reports.
12 mayor, council, community and now.
What exciting times are living in our?
I mean, it's pretty cool to see that people are coming.
going to our town and willing to invest in us because they believe in us and all around
from our animal control to everything we've got going on in, it's phenomenal, I'm just proud
that I've got to be part of it.
Thank you.
I want to say boys and girls club, the friends of Coleman, we've got that deal done this week.
Of course, we've got special meeting in Thursday to go around that and got that done.
So good thanks for the community there.
Steve Owens billboard, I got notes here on that one, so I'll make sure I'm missing
the Steve Owens billboard that's out by the welcome to my Amazon at the Steve
Owens and the turnpike.
I don't know if anybody's noticed with that.
That billboard up there is pretty faded and I don't know how it has been there anybody
now.
Just been here a while, but it's pretty faded out.
So we had a community member branch in our attention.
They did like to have it replaced.
That was former councilman, Neil Johnson, and the cost was $640 to replace that.
And that Colby Allen was going to replace it.
And I think Bo is going to get that taken care of and get that replaced before he leaves.
So he has to offer out of here.
I can actually get that there and do it.
No, no, no.
Not if you wanted to look.
But anyway, for that price, to get that replaced was pretty cheap.
I thought to have that, someone people can tell me.
See who of our legend's areas.
We got several.
And Steve's one of them.
And I think that's something else.
I'm going to piggyback off for a Brian's talking about a little bit about the people coming to town.
And David Davis is here in the course of the former councilman, but he's also a real estate guy in town.
And he can vouch that we get calls almost daily from somebody.
Or we're talking to somebody about a person's property or what's available.
It's exciting times right now because we haven't had that in a while.
You know, we got.
Elton Oppa is probably going to open within 30 days.
I would say.
And then papa is going to be starting next door.
Or Starbucks will all start coming up on it.
We saw this property today.
And the guy's going to do some exciting stuff downtown.
And other places in town.
But this lot of good stuff happened.
So like Brian said, it's exciting.
One of the people are believing in you like we believe in this.
So it's good to see that from outside the community.
So.
And then I don't have anything else in the bus.
Or gone.
This is most of the last councilman.
It is.
Is it?
Yeah, yeah.
We still have four days.
First of all, we can call special meeting.
So we'll move on to 13 to the City Matters final communication final communications.
Well, it's very, very bittersweet.
You know, of course I'm excited about the new opportunity that I'm going to be taking an advantage of,
but it was a very, very difficult decision to make because I do love what I do.
I love this town.
I love working with the City, and I like being a City Manager.
It's something that I think I said I was practicing for my entire life in state government
to see what I could come to here.
But I enjoy it greatly.
As life sometimes does, it throws your curve ball, and I was presented with an opportunity
that, as a husband and father and a grandfather, I just have to take advantage of.
That being said, you all know more than anything I value relationships,
and working here, I have developed a lot of working relationships with just friendships
and relationships with council members, with businesses, with our tribes,
and certainly with the employees who I think the world of.
I think we have some of the most amazing employees I've ever had in the pleasure of working with.
That's what keeps the City running for the employees.
We set up here and make decisions and give direction and set paths and have oversight.
And then these folks go out and they execute day after day after day after day after week and after special event after holiday after.
And it's never ending.
We have a lot of citizens to take care of this town, and they do an amazing job and they're very dedicated to it.
And often it goes unsung and unappreciated, and sometimes they often find themselves the target frustration.
But they do it again every day and it makes a difference just like with trees getting planted,
and basically standing up and showing her leadership and how she can change how we treat animals in this community.
They all make a difference every day.
And so we've worked really hard since I've been here to create a culture of supporting one another and lifting one another.
And I think we've made great strides in doing that.
And I'm really proud of the employees, and then the way we've been able to come together and communicate as a team.
We've made some great strides in showing the value to our employees through doing some wage assessments, as you all know.
And we've been able to really adjust how we budget in the city.
like prior in prior years, we spent a lot of our effort budgeting for things and we didn't
always take care of our people. And if we don't take care of our people, those things are
going to mean a whole lot when they're setting idle or setting unused. So we got to have
good people and we got to take care of our people and we've came a long way getting our cost
to the living adjustments in place so that we closed that gap that we had a significant wage gap.
And we've closed that. Now that doesn't include the unions because the unions were
not part of that study because the unions are negotiated separately. So I would tell you,
don't lose sight of our unions. We've got potentially some good agreements coming your way.
We've been negotiating for several weeks now. And I'm very excited for what I think is going
to come for your approval. Some multi-year agreements with our unions. And again, they
were all efforts to close the wage gap because we've got to take care of them too and make
sure we keep an eye on them and close that gap because we don't want to find ourselves so far behind
that we can't compete with local communities because our employees always have an option to work
here or work somewhere else and we want them to work here. As I get ready to exit, timing is really
bad because we're going to go into a budget cycle and tag in our new interim city manager to take
lead on those budget sessions. And of course the question every year is what is the budget going to
look like and what does the economy look like? And it's always trying to look into your crystal ball
and figure out where we're at today, where we're going to be tomorrow. And a lot of that's unknown,
but we look at trends, we look at our past trends and we look at future trends and try to figure out
what it's going to look like. And we've been trending very positively as you all know, we've had really good
times. It's been great. It's a horrible thing. It was great to us financially. It was really a kickstart
for our economy. And so we've had a lot of extra dollars flowing in our community, but we also had
inflation that was going up as we've all experienced. And that inflation did drive a lot of increases
in our sales tax collection. So we've seen our sales tax just climb dramatically. And that's a good thing.
So when you go to our budgets we go to our budgets and we're all though cautious and conservative when we
try to estimate future sales tax, knowing at what point maybe that was going to come down and it is
starting to plateau. So we've been on an incline and now we're starting to flatten out and we're not
dipping but we're plateauing. What we still want to be conservative to say, we don't know where that's
going to go exactly. But what we do know and the trends that we have seen is as inflation has stayed up
in the past several years, our availability to purchase things has been...
Everybody's had that problem, right supply chain issue. So it's really hard to get anything done
That also means it's really hard to spin money
So you've got high sales tax
We're trying to budget conservative, but we're budgeting some of that new sales tax and then we're not spending it all because we can't get things delivered
And so we end up with carryover
carryover is what we don't spend each year. We carry over to the next budget has revenue
The city generally runs on that carryover to some degree as revenue. So we anticipate it as revenue
So this year we've had a good year on sales tax
inflation still seems
Flesh and high which also means our cost of materials is high
But availability is coming back. So we're able to buy things. We're able to do things. We're able to expend funds
So our carryover is shrinking significantly
So as we go into this budget cycle what we are seeing preliminarily right now is that our carryover is smaller than normal
So it's showing a reduced revenue
So this is a time and I and right now it's it's early
Jill does what she can to really try to calculate
You know what trends she's seeing and that's all she could present is the numbers that she has
She can't read the future but she can kind of predict where we've had it if we continue on this
So what we have done at this point with three months left
Really in this fiscal year because we've gone to a central spending
Which means let's don't continue to spend at this rate even though availability is there so that we can try to
Contain that carryover for next year's budget
Because again when you go into next year's budget the first thing you want to go to do is budget for your people
You want to make sure that you can cover your cost of living and then we'll then you'll go in and focus on all the materials and other things
Right personal first
So that's first thing we're doing right now is we're in a central spending
So you'll hear that from staff
They're just trying to control this is something that Tyler and I've talked about so I'm not I'm not surprised and Tyler with it tonight
This has been something we've all been talking about as a group and
Then we're also looking at vacancies as a vacancy comes open
Do you really have to fill it right away or can you wait three months?
Because waiting three months you're kicking the candy on the road, but you're gonna retain some payroll laps from not having that filled for three months
And then you can budget it in next year's budget
Which again it helps our revenues as we look at the budget if we just don't fill it for three months now not everything can be done
If you've got a small apartment has two employees and you lose one, you're gonna need to fill that position
But some of the larger departments have that the ability to really evaluate
Can I wait three months and will it have a big negative impact right?
So
Those are things that I think is is important is just sharing with you all kind of where we're at
I didn't want to just leave all those surprises for Tyler to come share with you all
I'm gone if things continue to trend that we might
have a tight budget cycle this year, and it would be the first time post-COVID that we really
had kind of a tight situation.
We also continue to need to be evaluating our transfers from our MSUA.
Now, every year, that's one of the great benefits of having your own utility, is MSUA is able
to transfer to the general fund, and those funds help pay for public safety, police, and
fire, and streets, all kinds of things, but it's important that you keep a tight control
of that.
You want to understand how much is appropriate, how much should I be doing there?
That was trending very, very much in a high area when I got here.
It was up getting on its way to about 4 million a year, we're about half of that now.
We've been able to scale back, but things have been really good, so we've been able
to pull that back.
But that's something that you all will just have to really try to find that balance of how much
do you pull out of your utility, because again, that's going back to the citizens, just going back
and goods and services, but it also has a direct impact on how you maintain your infrastructure.
So you don't want to take too much away from your utility, so that you can't maintain your infrastructure.
All that to say, we don't know where we're going, we're trying to make the best decisions,
we can't be information that we have, something that's really resonated with me from what's
been a little bit back now was when David Davis stepped down.
He said, this is a time we ought to be betting on ourselves.
He's not wrong.
I mean, you all said here today and talk about all the things that are going on, great in
my amount, and it's because we're betting on ourselves.
My amount is getting out there, we're making decisions, anticipating the good things to come.
And so there's a little bit of that you have to do, you have to be willing to bet on yourselves.
So as you all go through your budget cycle and you try to anticipate the future, take care
of your employees and be conservative, don't forget to keep betting on yourselves, because
my amount is going to win every time, it pans down, so I appreciate every ounce of
every opportunity I've had to be a part of this for the last three years.
I thank you for giving me this opportunity, for bearing with me as the staff had to teach me how
to be a city manager, they did an amazing job, they were patient, they kind, and they're extremely
knowledgeable, and they all are very talented and capable, and whether I'm up here or not, they
all can run this organization every single day, and they do.
But that being said, thank you all so much for all the time, I got to spend here with you and
I hope to keep working in some capacity with the city, on other boards and efforts, as I
stay here in Miami and keep my family here, keep my grand babies here, and keep my image strong.
So, thank you all.
14 of granite. So move. You want a second, this one?
Okay, I can't, but I will.
Second. No, she says I can't.
Second Brad, speak up. What's on the line?
We said I can't go.
I'll take Williams.
Hi.
Perfect.